William A. H. Allen Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William A. H. Allen Papers 1863-1884
MSS10538
Allen, William A. H.
14 items 8 oversize containers 4 linear feet 3 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer and engineer. Journals with photographs, sketches, and illustrations describing Allen's activities while serving in the United States Navy during the Civil War, subsequently on ships in the Mediterranean, Indian, and Pacific Oceans, and at stations on the east and west coasts of the United States and Europe.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Allen, William A. H.
Organizations
Cayuga (Ship); United States. Navy --Foreign service--Europe.; United States. Navy --Foreign service--Indian Ocean.; United States. Navy --Foreign service--Mediterranean Sea.; United States. Navy --Foreign service--Pacific Ocean.
Places
Africa--Description and travel.; Asia--Description and travel.; China--Description and travel.; Egypt--Description and travel.; Japan--Description and travel.; Lebanon--Description and travel.; Malaya--Description and travel.; Middle East--Description and travel.; Palestine--Description and travel.; Peru--Description and travel.; Singapore--Description and travel.; Syria--Description and travel.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Blockades.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.
Occupations
Engineers.; Naval officers.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of William A. H. Allen, naval officer and engineer, were given to the Library of Congress by Mrs. William H. Steeble in 1952.
Additional Guides
A description of the collection was published in the Library’s Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions 12 no. 24 (June 25, 1953): 5-6.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William A. H. Allen are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on three reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
William A. H. Allen (fl. 1863-1890) was a United States naval officer and engineer who in 1863-1864, as an assistant engineer on the Cayuga (ship), participated in the blockading of Gulf Coast ports. He traveled to India and the Far East between 1866 and 1869, to Peru in 1875, and made an around-the-world cruise aboard the Lancaster (sloop-of-war) between 1881 and 1884.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William A. H. Allen (fl. 1863-1890) span the years 1863-1884. The collection consists of journals with photographs, sketches, and illustrations describing Allen's activities while serving on the Cayuga (ship), 1863-1864, assigned to blockade duty on the Gulf Coast during the Civil War, and subsequently on ships in the Mediterranean, Indian, and Pacific Oceans, and at stations on the east and west coasts of the United States and Europe, including on an around-the-world tour in 1881-1884 on the sloop-of-war Lancaster.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged chronologically by journal.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm73010538
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 19,595
- Blockade, Texas, 1863, 21 Mar.-1864, 31 May (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Trip around the world, Boston, Mass., to Manila, Philippines, via Ireland; Portugal; Cape Town, South Africa; Ceylon; Malaya; and Singapore, 1866, 30 May-31 Dec. (Box 2, Reel 1)
- Malaya and Singapore, 1866, Nov. (Box 3, Reel 1)
- China and Japan, 1868-1869 (Box 4, Reel 1)
- Various cities; San Francisco, Calif.; Chicago, Ill.; Philadelphia, Pa.; Norfolk, Va.; Savannah, Ga.; Havana, Cuba; Key West, Fla.; Rio de Janeiro, Brazil; and Valparaiso, Peru, 1869, 29 Aug.-1873, 6 Dec. (Box 5, Reel 1)
- San Francisco, Calif.; Valparaiso, Peru; Panama; North Africa; Western Europe; Genoa, Italy; La Havre, France; and Copenhagen, Denmark, 1874, 3 Jan.-1883, 4 Aug. (Box 6, Reel 2)
- Aríca, Calloá, and Lima [Peru and Chile], 1875 (Box 7, Reel 2)
- Europe; Nice, France; Villegranche, Spain; Monaco; and Genoa, Livornó, and Naples, Italy, 1881-1884 (Box 8, Reel 2)
- Damascus, Syria, 1881-1884 (Box 9, Reel 2)
- Damascus, Syria, and Lebanon, 1881-1884 (Box 10, Reel 2)
- Beirut and Saida (Sidon), Lebanon; and Tsoor, Akka, and Haifa, Palestine, 1881-1884 (Box 11, Reel 2)
- Holy Land, Carmel, Jaffa, Jerusalem, Dead Sea, Jericho, Bethlehem, and Hebron, 1881-1884 (Box 12, Reel 3)
- Syria and Egypt (Cairo omitted), 1881-1884 (Box 13, Reel 3)
- Villegranche, Spain; Port Mahon, Minorca; Cadiz, Spain; Gibraltar; Malaga and Cartagena, Spain; Algiers, Algeria; Messina, Italy; Alexandria, Egypt; Lisbon, Portugual; and New York, 4 Sept. 1883-20 Aug. 1884 (Box 14, Reel 3)